Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.22
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series XXII. Awards, Gifts and Memorabilia
1950-2007
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.22
628 items
The Awards, Gifts and Memorabilia series in the Dick Thornburgh Papers consists of physical items that he received throughout his distinguished career. While most items pertain to Dick Thornburgh, some are also shared with Ginny Thornburgh, and some are to her alone. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998.
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Women; Pennsylvania -- Officials and employees -- Awards; United States -- Officials and employees -- Awards; Plaques (Flat objects); Memorabilia; Souvenirs (Keepsakes); Plaques, plaquettes; University of Pittsburgh; Government; Politics; Personal papers; Social action; Education; Thornburgh, Dick -- Awards; Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson) -- Awards
- Awards, Gifts and Memorabilia, 1950-2007; XXII.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series in the collection consists of awards, gifts and memorabilia that Thornburgh received throughout his distinguished career. While most items pertain to Dick Thornburgh, some are also shared with Ginny Thornburgh, and some are to her alone (the latter are described separately).
  There are numerous degrees and honorary degrees, plaques that enumerate accomplishments and important occasions, and many varied awards, certificates, and certifications. Some are more decorative or distinctive than others, and such positive attributes have been enumerated. Having had a twenty-five year public service career, and a subsequent active and ongoing legal career, such presentations and gifts are familiar. They well represent the esteem felt by organizations and individuals for the notable work and contributions to society of both Dick and Ginny Thornburgh. In some cases these items may be the only references to related accomplishments.
  The items are arranged by era (e.g., youth, education, ongoing career, etc.) or public service position (Governor, Attorney General of the U.S., etc). Each item description is preceded by format or type of item received: plaque, degree, gift, certificate, photograph, award, certification, poster, proclamation, honorary degree, and Ginny Thornburgh. Many are ideal for displays as well as serving as a source of information.
  The item designation "Oversize" followed by a number, refers to a physical location within the archive, and not to the size of the item itself.
  - Youth and Education, 1.
    - Degree: University of Pittsburgh School of Law, June 12, 1957 (Oversize 8)
    - Award: University of Pittsburgh Law Review, "Performed meritorious service as Case Editor" University of Pittsburgh Law Review, March 28, 1957 (Oversize 125)
    - Award: University of Pittsburgh Law Review, Order of the Coif, "High attainments in the study of Law", June 1957
    - Degree: Mercersburg Diploma, June 5, 1950 (Oversize 128)
    - Degree: Yale University: Richard Lewis Thornburgh, Bachelor Degree in Engineering [Framed], June 7, 1954
  - Early Legal Career, 2.
    - Certificate: Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Admitting Richard Lewis Thornburgh to practice before it, March 17, 1958 (Oversize 18)
    - Certificate: Superior Court of Pennsylvania, Admitting Richard Lewis Thornburgh to practice before it, April 13, 1964 (Oversize 19)
    - Certification: United States of America Western District of PA, Admitted and qualified as an Attorney, Counselor, Solicitor, Advocate, and Proctor, February 13, 1958 (Oversize 125)
    - Certification: American Judicature Society Voting member of and supporter of its program "To Promote the Efficient Administration of Justice", 1961
    - Certificate: American Bar Association Membership, 1962-1963
    - Certification: Interstate Commerce Commission Richard L. Thornburgh enrolled and admitted to practice, Signed, certified copy, June 3, 1963
    - Pennsylvania Bar Association Certification: Having beenelected Member of board of Governors, 1963, Richard L. Thornburgh served with "honor and distinction", June 23, 1965
  - Campaign for U.S. Congress, 3.
    - Photograph: Huge hard back photo, c. 4'x6' Dick Thornburgh, Governor William Scranton, and Lt. Governor Raymond Shafer, 1966 (Oversize 116)
  - Pennsylvania Constitutional Convention, 4.
    - Certificate: Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Richard Lewis Thornburgh elected delegate to Constitutional Convention of 1966-68, Signed by James A. Michener, Secretary, February 15, 1968 (Oversize 21)
    - Photograph: Panoramic view of Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Constitutional Convention [Framed: 2'7" x 1'x1/2"], 1967-1968 (Oversize 72)
  - United States Attorney, 5.
    - Plaque: Pittsburgh Jaycees Man of the Year [with Point photo], 1975 (Oversize 9)
    - Gift: Framed colored pencil drawing from trial of Tony Grosso, early 1970s, Dick Thornburgh and two other persons in court, ca. 1970s (Oversize 20)
    - Certificate: Richard M. Nixon, President of USA, Appointing Richard Lewis Thornburgh United States Attorney for Western PA, May 19, 1979 (Oversize 22)
    - Plaque: Pittsburgh Jaycees, Saluting "Pittsburgh's 1975 Man of the Year, Richard Lewis Thornburgh" [With drawing of Point, photo and bio, and other honorees in smaller pictures; back cracked] (Oversize 25)
    - Gift: Autographed Dept. of Justice Seal (Oversize 34)
    - Cartoon: Post Gazette Hungerford cartoon, of PA PITT Waving goodbye to Thornburgh: "We will miss you – Dick!" [Thornburgh off to Assistant Attorney General Position in D.C.; Large framed], 1975 (Oversize 74)
    - Flag: Huge flag. Justice emblem on grey background, with United States Attorney above the eagle. (Oversize 123)
    - Certificate: Squirrel Hill Kiwanis Club… Appreciation, March 16, 1972 (Oversize 125)
    - Proclamation: City of Pittsburgh Honoring Thornburgh's 40th birthday By Peter Flaherty, Mayor, July 16, 1972
    - Award: University and City Ministries Special Award to Richard and Virginia Thornburgh, United States Attorney and Activist for PARC: "Co-workers for human values and Representatives of creative interaction of Church, University and Society", November 3, 1973
    - Certificate: American Bar Foundation, Fellow of American Bar Foundation, 1975
    - Award: Lions Club of Pittsburgh, Man of the Year, "...devotion to duty beyond the normal expectations in the fulfillment of responsibilities for the maintaining of a better country for all mankind", June 4, 1975
    - Award: Certificate of Service, Richard L. Thornburgh, United States Attorney, In appreciation and recognition of meritorious services, As member of Attorney General's Advisory Committee of U.S. Attorneys Signed: Edward H. Levi, Attorney General, July 6, 1975
    - Award: Federal Executive Board of US Attorneys:Commendation for outstanding performance as U.S. Attorney, June 19, 1975
    - Plaque: Large with photo of Point. "1970 Law 1979, Man of the Year, Richard L. Thornburgh: For Dedicated Community Service, Presented by The Pittsburgh Jaycees, [Top brass plaque scratched. Collection includes photo from the occasion.], January 24, 1971 (Oversize 160)
    - Plaque: Brass lettering plaque only (not the original wooden backing), Fancy looking brass emblem of US Department of Justice, Bureau of Narcotics & Dangerous Drugs. "Richard L. Thornburgh, United States Attorney, Western District of Pennsylvania, Presented in recognition of your significant personal efforts to help eliminate drug abuse.", June 29, 1973
    - Gift: Framed Pencil Drawing of Dick Thornburgh with glasses, unsigned [Nice] (Oversize 165)
    - Gift: Framed Black and White ink drawing of Attorney General's Entrance to DOJ, framed in glass [nice]
    - Plaque: Variety Club Man of the Year, October 20, 1974
    - Plaque: To Richard Lewis Thornburgh, US Marshalls Service, "…for exceptional service", November 19, 1975 (Oversize 173)
    - Plaque: Chartiers Valley Chamber of Commerce, Man of Distinction Award, 1971
    - Plaque: Pittsburgh Business Show, In appreciation, Keynote Speaker, A.S.M. Pittsburgh Chapter, 1977
    - Plaque: Citizen of the Year, Pittsburgh Lions Club, 1975
    - Plaque: United States Attorney, Greater Latrobe Chamber of Commerce, 30th Annual Meeting, October 21, 1974
    - Award: To Richard Lewis Thornburgh Assistant Attorney General U.S. Department of Justice, August 29, 1975
    - Award: Mounted badge, DOJ Drug Enforcement Administration, August 29, 1975
    - Award: To Richard Lewis Thornburgh Dauphin County Chiefs of Police Association, Guest Speaker, Annual Dinner, February 18, 1978
    - Award: Honored by Hempfield Township, October 8, 1977
  - Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division, 6.
    - Poster: "In Honor of Richard Lewis Thornburgh, United States Attorney 1969-75, Assistant Attorney General, head of Criminal Division, 1975-77" [Dept. of Justice seal in background; three unframed extras] (Oversize 23)
    - Honorary Degree: Washington & Jefferson College, Doctor of Laws, May 29, 1978 (Oversize 130)
    - Photograph: Attorney General Levi and Assistant Attorneys General (Oversize 160)
    - Plaque: Shield shaped: Outstanding service to Criminal Division, To Assistant Attorney General Richard Lewis Thornburgh, 1975-1977
    - Award: Boxed large gold "coin," To Assistant US Attorney General, Department of Justice from Philadelphia Bar Association, March 11, 1976 (Oversize 167)
    - Award: University of Pittsburgh clear paper weight, Graphic of Law School Building, Building Dedication, Law Day, Richard L. Thornburg [no "h"'], 1976
    - Plaque: To Honorable Richard L. Thornburgh, NORTHEASTERN MARYLAND LAW ENFORCEMENT ASSOCIATION: Wooden plaque with mounted wooden billy-club [Plaque loose, in envelope], June 9, 1976
  - Campaign for Governor, 7.
    - Cartoon: Turtle en route to statehouse, "They laughed when I started,", 1978 (Oversize 2)
    - Cartoon: Grosso for Revenue Secretary (Oversize 3)
    - Cartoon: Dick Thornburgh a tattered wounded football player, Scoreboard: Thornburgh 39 - Flaherty 51, Thornburgh: "Haven't you ever heard of momentum"[Time of publication: PA election polls], October, 1978 (Oversize 4)
    - Plaque: In appreciation of Richard L. Thornburgh from Western PA Legislative Council of Construction Employers,[large scratch], October 28, 1977 (Oversize 26)
    - Cartoon: Timenees, Lieutenant Governor Candidate Casey in inner tube behind Flaherty boat: "Let 'er rip", July, 1978 (Oversize 41)
    - Poster: Thornburgh photo, "Thornburgh for Governor". [Fragile wrapping – not protected by cardboard – large] (Oversize 47)
    - Cartoon: Timenees, Very small meeting with candidate Thornburgh!, July 1978 (Oversize 73)
    - Cartoon: Post Primary '78, Thornburgh in "white knight" armor Being hoisted up onto elephant by the GOP Primary losers: Watson, Specter, Hager, Marston, and Bob Butera. [Large, framed. Wonderful!], 1978 (Oversize 75)
    - Photograph: Close-up of Dick and Ginny; Ginny has Thornburgh/Scranton campaign button on. [heavy, strong backing; color; nice!] (Oversize 78)
    - Certificate: Greater Connellsville Chamber of CommerceAppreciation, Thornburgh Speaker at Annual Dinner, September 29, 1977 (Oversize 125)
    - Certificate: Washington Lions Club, Appreciation, Thornburgh Guest Speaker, October 1, 1977
    - Certificate: Civil Air Patrol: Richard L. Thornburgh appointed Honorary Member [with emblem]
    - Award: Dauphin County Chiefs of Police Association, Guest Speaker, Annual Dinner, February 18, 1978 (Oversize 173)
    - Award: Honored by Hempfield Township, October 8, 1977
  - Re-election Campaign, 8.
    - Two graphic framed small posters: Thornburgh WINS and other Ertel WINS with line through it. (Oversize 108)
    - Poster: Multiple posters with photo of Governor Thornburgh saying: "Governor Thornburgh He's making a real difference" (Oversize 109)
    - Poster: With accomplishments of Thornburgh first term in education, boldly presented (Oversize 112)
  - Governor of Pennsylvania, 9.
    - Cartoon: Thornburgh Fishing for Jobs, Attorney General, President, etc …"fulfilling retirement" (Oversize 7)
    - Plaque: Triangular name plaque, Republican Governors Association [Elephant Insignia], 1979 (Oversize 10)
    - Photograph: Framed of Ginny and Governor Thornburgh in Governor's Home in front of fireplace, 1980 (Oversize 27)
    - Certificate: Susquehanna University citation with photograph of the awarding his honorary degree, [Degree itself with other Honorary Degrees], May 22, 1983 (Oversize 37)
    - Award: Crystal sculpture Ben Franklin Technology Champion Award, To Governor Dick Thornburgh, "a man of principle, vision, and leadership." [Very handsome (and heavy!) original sculpture, designed by Peter Wayne Yenawine. Special light and cleaning instructions in box; provision for electrical spotlighting if natural light not available in separate wrapping; instructions re cleaning etc also there in envelope], March 3, 2003 (Oversize 49)
    - Gift: Two Scrapbooks from Homestead Works, USS: Prepared for Dick Thornburgh visit. A second scrapbook prepared for Ginny Thornburgh visit January 1980. [Preservation concerns but usable and reflect interesting era of steel in Pennsylvania], April 19, 1979 (Oversize 50)
    - Award: Large framed drawing of children, one in wheelchair – with brass plaque: "With gratitude for opening a world of possibilities for children with disabilities, Dick and Ginny Thornburgh, 2003 Betts Award Recipients, You Inspire Us, Achieva" [Very significant award!], June 19, 2003 (Oversize 53)
    - Poster: Bound charts of ads regarding the PA economy Comparing PA with other states. (Oversize 54)
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Laws, Lehigh University, October 12, 1980 (Oversize 55)
    - Photo: Dick Thornburgh at Armco Inc [frame dented & tape stuck to front], 1980 (Oversize 56)
    - Plaque: Small Business Advocates of the Year to Dick Thornburgh [Photograph of the Point, scratches], Sept. 18, 1981 (Oversize 57)
    - Plaque: Mercersburg Academy to Dick ThornburghCommemorates 1983 Ellesmere Island Arctic Expedition, PA flag and photo of explorers, 1'8 1/2"x1'4"x3/4". Flag was carried to memorial service at Pim Island. [Very interesting!] (Oversize 60)
    - Plaque: Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith to Dick Thornburgh [Pretty glass overlaying drawing, frame dented], June 12, 1980 (Oversize 61)
    - Plaque: Honeywell's Pittsburgh BOSS network to Dick Thornburgh [interesting - drop of oil encased in glass "bubble"], June 20, 1980 (Oversize 62)
    - Award: PA Library Assn. to Dick Thornburgh, October 16, 1984 (Oversize 63)
    - Certificate: President Ronald Reagan to Dick Thornburgh, appointed to Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations (ACIR), June 16, 1983 (Oversize 64)
    - Photo: Dick Thornburgh speaking in front of TMI towers, ca. 1981 (Oversize 66)
    - Photo: Memorabilia from Inaugural Ball [interesting collage], January 18, 1993 (Oversize 67)
    - Plaque: From New York Water Company To Dick Thornburgh [Piece of 19th century water pipe. Interesting!], 1984 (Oversize 71)
    - Cartoon: By Harsh, Thornburgh in "Three Mile Island Crisis," pictured as "COOL HEAD OF STATE!" Holds paper: " Senate Hearings," three other persons, nuclear expert, Met-Ed, NRC, running with heads off. [Large framed], April 25, 1979 (Oversize 76)
    - Photograph: Matt Ryan, looking over shoulder of Governor Thornburgh. Autographed: "To my Leader – The Governor – Careful, 'Big Brother' is watching - [signed] Matt Ryan". [Ryan was GOP Head PA House of Representatives] (Oversize 77)
    - Award: "Copper" Adidas shoe on base [heavy]: "Governor Thornburgh in commemoration of one millionth pair of Adidas shoes made in Kutztown, PA" [unboxed], September 1982 (Oversize 79)
    - Award: Tall, handsome wooden horse (c. 20") carving from Auwaerter Family during visit to Stuttgart, Germany[He Chairman of Board of Neoplan] [Unboxed], June 5, 1982 (Oversize 80)
    - Award: To Governor "Recipient of Friend of Israel Award"Jewish National Fund [sculpture in shape of Shalom in Hebrew] [Unboxed.], Feb. 2, 1986 (Oversize 81)
    - Award: Colored "icon" print, to Governor Dick Thornburgh and Ginny Thornburgh…by B'nai Brith Lancaster, PA, July 1985 (Oversize 82)
    - Plaque: To Governor Richard Thornburgh, PA Wing Civil Air Patrol [Seal loose], 1980 (Oversize 83)
    - Certificate: Gold seal certificate to Dick and Ginny Thornburgh, Flag Day, Abington, PA, "…selfless service to our Commonwealth…sincere concern for Handicapped…", June 4, 1982 (Oversize 84)
    - Award: Framed Letter with ribbon and seal,; from James A. Baker III to Dick Thornburgh, re "service to US Savings Bonds program", December 11, 1985 (Oversize 86)
    - Plaque: To Governor Richard Thornburgh, from Lodge of Fraternal Order of Police; "…untiring efforts…toward law enforcement…" [elaborate], August 11, 1982 (Oversize 89)
    - Plaque: To Richard L. Thornburgh, Governor, in appreciation from Harrisburg Y.M.C.A. [Photo] (Oversize 90)
    - Award: To Dick and Ginny Thornburgh, "…first Charter Members of the Friends of the PA Historical and Museum Commission…preservation of our Commonwealth's Historic Heritage…", undated (Oversize 91)
    - Plaque: "Excellent Performance as Governor…outstanding support of Asian- Americans" by SANG IK PARK, Chairman Asian-American Governor's Dinner, 1982 (Oversize 92)
    - Plaque: Decorative copper panels, To Dick Thornburgh "...for honoring recipients of First Annual Governor's Awards for Excellence in the Arts, Harrisburg, PA, May 1, 1980 (Oversize 93)
    - Plaque: "To Richard Thornburgh "…outstanding service…" From North City Congress [Elaborate], June 18, 1982 (Oversize 94)
    - Plaque: "Welcome to Richard Thornburgh and best wishes… visit to Los Angeles County, by Board of Supervisors [elaborate], undated (Oversize 95)
    - Plaque: Wood carving on copper: "…commitment to Veterans…:from Department of Veterans of Foreign Wars; [Small metal plaque loose, taped to back], June 25, 1981 (Oversize 96)
    - Plaque: Honorary membership from American Subcontractors Association of PA, January 1980 (Oversize 97)
    - Plaque: From Greater Erie Community Action Committee: "…effort to assist minority business in Erie…", September 20, 1983 (Oversize 98)
    - Plaque: "…dedication to peace and brotherhood…" from United Korean Association of PA [elaborate], March 13, 1982 (Oversize 99)
    - Plaque: Distinguished service certificate [under "glass"] "…outstanding service to community state and nation…" From American Legion, 1984 (Oversize 100)
    - Plaque:"…continuing support to betterment of agriculture." From Farmers Association [elaborate], 1983 (Oversize 101)
    - Plaque: Elaborate, interesting colorful design. From Jewish National Fund; "…woodland planted…in honor of Governor Dick Thornburgh…" Pottstown, King of Prussia Area [Undated], March 10, 1981 (Oversize 102)
    - Gift: Thornburgh Campaign for Governor campaign buttons mounted and framed – each a different country or peoples: Chinese for Thornburgh, etc. [Fun!] (Oversize 103)
    - Wooden shield shaped award with lettering " Special Olympics" (Oversize 104)
    - Gift: LARGE long (c. 8'x10') banner: "THORNBURGH". Letters in gold, background blue. [Has grommets so can be easily hung – impressive!] (Oversize 105)
    - Plaque: Heavy square good looking wooden plaque with round gold metal image of the state capital on it. [Good looking] (Oversize 106)
    - Photographs: Two framed photos of PAT bus and trolley with Steelers logos on them: from Jim Maloney, chairman of PAT, 1980 (Oversize 107)
    - Poster: Large BOLD framed poster: "Commit a crime with a gun here and you've shot 5 years of your life." "Pennsylvania has a new law. Commit a crime with a gun and you're in prison for five years. No deals. No parole. No exceptions. Five years in prison. …Pennsylvania Committee for Effective Justice." (Oversize 110)
    - Certificate: Framed Gold sealed certificate acknowledging Governor's assistance with new Bidwell Training Center in Pittsburgh, and photograph, October, 1986 (Oversize 111)
    - Photograph: Framed large color nice formal photograph of Governor, with gold plaque:" Erie Centennial year…Governor Dick Thornburgh in testimony of his outstanding efforts on behalf of PA Veterans and in appreciation for improving quality of life at the PA Soldiers' and Sailors' Home.", Undated (Oversize 113)
    - Gift: Framed pencil drawing/sketch of Thornburgh. Presented by the city of Farrell, 1983 (Oversize 114)
    - Photographs: Two huge hard back photos, c. 4' x 6'. Governor in front of TMI Tower (1981) and other of Governor and Ginny informal [really nice], 1979 (Oversize 115)
    - Photographs: For Legacy Brochure [Governor brochure], 1987 (Oversize 119)
    - Photographs: For Legacy Brochure [Governor brochure], 1987 (Oversize 120)
    - Photograph: Thornburgh family photo, seated in Gov's Home by fireplace (Oversize 121)
    - Photograph: Formal Governor Thornburgh photo, wearing glasses, ca. 1979
    - Photograph: Governor Dick Thornburgh and Ginny by fireplace in Governor's Home [wearing glasses], ca. 1979-1980
    - Photograph: Governor with Cabinet on lawn of Governor's Home, 1986
    - Photograph: Large nicely matted color photo: Governor Thornburgh Cabinet [he's not in picture], November 1984 (Oversize 122)
    - Photographs: Large matted color photographs "Pennsylvania Migrant Education", May 6, 1985
    - Photograph: Large B&W photo poster: Governor "Thornburgh: A Day in the Life," Express, Short paragraph: "A Capitol Day" [scratch on Governor's face in one picture but nice overall.], September 18, 1983
    - Gift: Huge blue satin "Governor Thornburgh" banner [estimated size 6' x 12' from Governor re-elect campaign '82 (Oversize 123)
    - Certificate: Opportunities Industrialization Centers of America, Inc Appreciation "…special concern for the unemployed, underemployed and unemployable Americans…Executive Government Award…", Undated (Oversize 126)
    - Certification: Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Gold seal signed Teller's Report, certifying the victories of Thornburgh and Scranton [Same in January, 1983], January 2, 1979
    - Certificate: University of Pittsburgh Law Alumni Association, "To Richard L. Thornburgh, distinguished alumnus of the University of Pittsburgh School of Law, wise counselor, able administrator, tireless prosecutor, ardent advocate of integrity, we hereby extend our highest commendation for the application of your ideals which have contributed to the administration of justice and betterment of government and offer our sincere congratulations on your inauguration this date as the forty-first GOVERNOR OF THE COMMONWEALTH OF PENNSYLVANIA", January 16, 1979
    - Certificate: Honorary Sheriffs and Long Rifle Association ….Distinguished list of…, July 4, 1979
    - Certificate: Appreciation "…in grateful recognition of outstanding service to PA Vietnam War Veterans.", November 1, 1979
    - Certificate: PA Crime Prevention Officers Association"…appreciation for his outstanding leadership and supportive efforts in the field of crime prevention we …bestow this certificate…conscious of our never ending concern for this commonwealth and its citizens… proclaim, honorary member of PA Crime Prevention Officers Association" (oversized hand lettered certificate), May 13, 1980
    - Certificate: Department of the Treasury, USA, U.S. Savings Bond Division appointed DT honorary chairman of PA Savings Bond Committee [recognizing his patriotism, integrity and diligence], April 2, 1979
    - Certificate: PA Dept. of Military Affairs Humorous certificate:….Honorary Five Star General, February 8, 1980